Preliminary Guide to the Collection of Bookplates from British Institutions
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates from British Institutions
1700-1950
1800-1899
BKP 55
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection comprises mostly 18th- and 19th-century bookplates from a variety of British institutions, including libraries, social organizations, military organizations, schools and colleges as well as businesses.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library, Room 608. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises mostly 18th- and 19th-century bookplates from a variety of British institutions, including libraries, social organizations, military organizations, schools and colleges as well as businesses.
Arrangement
Organized into ten series: I. Parochial and Ecclesiastical Libraries. II. Circulating and Public Libraries. III. Clubs and Other Social Organizations. IV. Military Organizations. V. Schools and Colleges. VI. Premiums. VII. Universal Bookplates. VIII. Unidentified Bookplates. IX. Dr. John S. Pearson Collection of Bookplates from British Institutions.
Arranged alphabetically by the name of the institution. Whenever multiple bookplates from different organizations are affixed to the same mount, these are filed at the end of the series in a "Miscellaneous" folder or folders. Some of the miscellaneous items are duplicates of those appearing earlier in the series, whereas others are new to the series.
Bookplates, British; Bookplates
- Parochial and Ecclesiastical Libraries, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes bookplates from a variety of parochial and ecclesiastical libraries.
  - Martin Benson, Bishop of Gloucester – York Minister, 1742-1847 undated; 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous parochial and ecclesiastical libraries, undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous parochial and ecclesiastical libraries, 1821-1833 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous parochial and ecclesiastical libraries, 1732-1826 undated; 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous parochial and ecclesiastical libraries, 1737 circa 1800 undated; 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Circulating and Public Libraries, Series II
  This series includes bookplates from both circulating libraries and municipal free public libraries.
  - Bally's Circulating Library – Dumbarton Library, 1815 1825 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Falkirk Public Library – Liverpool Library, 1758-1876 undated; 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manchester Circulating Library – Plymouth Proprietary Library, undated; 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reference Library (Buckingham Palace Rd.) – Worcester Library, 1790-1890 undated; 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bookseller's Labels
    Booksellers often offered circulating library services.
    - Adolphe – Withers, undated; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
      This folder also contains a plate for Adolphe Art Photographer and Miniature Painter, 75 Grafton St., Dublin.
  - Miscellaneous circulating and public libraries, 1892 undated; 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Clubs and Other Social Organizations, Series III
  This series includes bookplates from a wide variety of social organizations.
  - Archaeological Society (London) – Inner Temple Library, 1824-1901 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    This folder contains a record of subscribers' names as well as dates for when a book was delivered by and returned to the Godalming Book Society.
  - Louth Book-Club – Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts, 1704-1882 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Society of Antiquaries of London – Working Men's Club, 1894 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    This folder contains an ex-libris design for the Royal Watercolour Society. The design features a landscape with a monument in the foreground, listing members' names and capped with a palette labeled "Water Colours."
  - Miscellaneous clubs and other social organizations, 1805-1846 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous clubs and other social organizations, 1765-1825 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This folder contains a membership list in the order of circulation along with dates for the Castle-Gate Junior Book-Society.
  - Miscellaneous clubs and other social organizations, 1839-1916 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    This folder contains a bookplate for the Ex Libris Lodge, No. 3765, a Freemason organization founded in London in 1915 by bookplate enthusiasts. This bookplate was designed by J. A. C. Harrison.
  - Miscellaneous clubs and other social organizations, 1878 undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Military Organizations, Series IV
  This series includes bookplates from a variety of military organizations.
  - 67th Regiment – Royal Naval School, 1763-1879 undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous military organizations, 1842 undated; 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Schools and Colleges, Series V
  This series includes bookplates from a variety of schools and colleges, ranging from grammar school to university.
  - Blackheath Proprietary School – Presbyterian College of England, 1841 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Queen's College, Cork – Winchester College, 1746 1760 undated; 17 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous schools and colleges, 1869 undated; 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Premiums, Series VI
  This series includes prize bookplates – also known as premiums. Schools often presented students with books as a reward; starting in the 18th century, these books typically included a bookplate inscribed with the name of the student and the subject or other reason for recognition.
  - The Association Incorporated for Discountenancing Vice and Promoting the Knowledge & Practice of the Christian Religion – St. Peter's College (Westminster, London, England), 1779-1866 undated; 14 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland), circa 1700-1869 undated; 52 items (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous premiums, circa 1700-1885 undated; 18 items (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Universal Bookplates, Series VII
  This series includes universal bookplates, which are ex-libris designs that are typically available commercially and allow the owner to insert his or her own name.
  - Miscellaneous universal bookplates, undated; 17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Unidentified Bookplates, Series VIII
  This series includes mostly unidentified armorial bookplates, although it also includes a few unidentified pictorial ex-libris designs as well.
  - Miscellaneous unidentified bookplates, undated; 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Dr. John S. Pearson Collection of Bookplates from British Institutions, Series IX
  This series includes a group of British institutional bookplates housed in an envelope addressed to Dr. J. S. Pearson.
  - Dr. John S. Pearson Collection, 1800-1950 undated; 14 bookplates; 2 envelopes (Box 1, Folder 29)